Some of the greatest innovations
بعضًا من أعظم الابتكارات
and developments in the world
والتطورات في العالم
often happen at the intersection of two fields.
حدثت غالبا عند تقاطع مجالين مختلفين.
So tonight I'd like to tell you
لذلك أود أن أحدثكم هذه الليلة
about the intersection that I'm most excited about at this very moment,
حول تقاطع أجد جُل حماستي وشغفي منصب بهما هذه اللحظة ،
which is entertainment and robotics.
وهما الترفيه والروبوتات.
So if we're trying to make robots
لذا إن حاولنا جعل الروبوتات
that can be more expressive
أكثر مقدرة على التعبير
and that can connect better with us in society,
وبإمكانها أن تتواصل معنا بشكل أفضل في مجتمعاتنا،
maybe we should look to some of the human professionals
ربما ينبغي أن ننظر إلى بعض المهن لدينا نحن البشر
of artificial emotion and personality
العاطفة الاصطناعية والسمات الشخصية
that occur in the dramatic arts.
التي تظهر في الفنون الدرامية.
I'm also interested in creating new technologies for the arts
أنا أيضا مهتمة في إنشاء تكنولوجيا جديدة للفنون
and to attract people
ولجذب الناس
to science and technology.
للعلوم والتكنولوجيا.
Some people in the last decade or two
بعض الناس في العقد أو العقدين الماضيين
have started creating artwork with technology.
بدأو في إنشاء ودمج الأعمال الفنية مع التكنولوجيا.
With my new venture, Marilyn Monrobot,
مع مشروعي الجديد ، مارلين مونروبوت ،
I would like to use art to create tech.
أود أن استخدام الفن لاستحداث التكنولوجيا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we're based in New York City.
نحن نقيم في مدينة نيويورك.
And if you're a performer that wants to collaborate
لذا إن كنت من مؤدي العروض المسرحية و تريد أن تتعاون
with an adorable robot,
مع الروبوت اللطيف ،
or if you have a robot that needs entertainment representation,
أو كان لديك الروبوت الذي يحتاج إلى الترفيه ،
please contact me, the Bot-Agent.
الرجاء الاتصال بي ، وكيلة البوت.
The bot, our rising celebrity,
البوت ، مشهورنا الواعد ،
also has his own Twitter account: @robotinthewild.
كما أن لديه حسابه الخاص على تويتر : @ robotinthewild.
I'd like to introduce you to one of our first robots, Data.
لذلك أود أن أعرفكم على أحد أول الروبوتات، داتا.
He's named after the Star Trek character.
أسميناه تبعًا للشخصية المشهورة في (ستار تراك)
I think he's going to be super popular.
اعتقد انه سيكون ذو شعبية.
We've got the robot --
لقد حصلنا على الروبوت --
in his head is a database of a lot of jokes.
في رأسه قاعدة بيانات بها الكثير من النكات.
Now each of these jokes is labeled with certain attributes.
الآن كل من هذه النكات ترتبط بها سمات معينة.
So it knows something about the subject; it knows about the length.
لذلك فهو يدرك شيئا عن الموضوع ، ويعرف طولها.
It knows how much it's moving.
كما يعرف عن مدى تحركها.
And so it's going to try to watch your response.
ذلك فهو سيحاول مشاهدة ردة فعلكم.
I actually have no idea what my robot is going to do today.
في الحقيقة ليس لدي أدنى فكرة عن ما سيقوم به روبوتي اليوم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It can also learn from you
لذلك يمكن أن تتعلم منكم أيضًا
about the quality of its jokes
عن جودة نكاتها
and cater things, sort of like Netflix-style,
وتلبية الأشياء -- على غرار Netflix --
over longer-term
على المدى الطويل
to different communities or audiences,
للمجتمعات المختلفة أو للجماهير --
children versus adults, different cultures.
الأطفال مقابل البالغين ، والثقافات المختلفة.
You can learn something from the robot
يمكنكم أن تتعلموا شيئا من الروبوت
about the community that you're in.
عن المجتمع الذي أنتم فيه.
And also I can use each one of you as the acting coach
وكذلك يمكن استخدام كل واحد منكم كمدرب
to our future robot companions.
لأصحابنا روبوتات المستقبل.
Some of you in this middle section --
لذا أود من البعض في القسم المتوسط
you have red/green paddles.
لديكم لافتات حمراء / وخضراء.
If you like what's going on,
إن أعجبكم ما يقوله
show the green.
فأظهروا اللافتة الخضراء.
If you don't like the subject or the performance,
أما إن لم يعجبكم الموضوع أو الأداء،
you can hold the red.
بإمكانكم حمل اللافتة الحمراء.
Now don't be shy.
لا تخجلوا.
It's just a robot.
انه مجرد روبوت ؛
It doesn't have feelings ... yet.
ليس لديه مشاعر... حتى الان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the rest of you,
أما البقية منكم ،
you still count, you still matter.
لا زلتم في الحسبان، ورأيكم مهم كذلك.
There's also a microphone
يوجد ميكروفون مدمج
that's listening to the aggregate laughter and applause
بإمكانه الاستماع إلى الضحك والتصفيق
and booing -- I hope not --
وأصوات الاستهجان -- لا آمل ذلك --
to help make some of its next decisions.
للمساعدة في اتخاذ بعض قراراته التالية.
Right, so,
حسناً ،
let the robot stand-up comedy begin.
لنتابع معًا عرض الروبوت الكوميدي.
Data: Hello TEDWomen.
داتا : مرحبا TEDWomen.
It's an honor to be here.
إنه لشرف لي أن أكون هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You guys are looking good out there.
تبدون في حالة جيدة هنا يا رفاق.
Ready for some jokes?
مستعدون لبعض النكات؟
Audience: Yeah.
(الجمهور : نعم.)
Data: Here's the first one.
ها هي أول واحدة.
Right, so,
حسنا ،
a doctor says to his patient,
يقول الطبيب لمريضه ،
"I have bad news and worse news.
"لدي أخبار سيئة وأخبار أسوأ.
The bad news is that you only have 24 hours to live."
أما النبأ السيئ هو أن لديك فقط 24 ساعة لتعيش ".
"That's terrible," said the patient.
فقال المريض "هذا فظيع".
"How can the news possibly be worse?"
"كيف يمكن أن بكون هناك خبر أسوأ؟"
"I've been trying to contact you since yesterday."
"لقد كنت أحاول الاتصال بك منذ يوم امس".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The Swiss have an interesting army. Five hundred years without a war.
السويسريون لديهم جيش مثير للاهتمام. خمس مئة سنة من دون حرب.
Heather Knight: He's talking about the Swiss.
هيذر نايت : انه يتحدث عن السويسريين.
Data: Pretty lucky for them.
داتا : يا لهم من محظوظين.
Ever see that little Swiss Army knife
هل رأيتم السكين السوسرية الصغيرة
they have to fight with?
التي يقاتلون بها؟
"Come on buddy, I have the toe clippers right here.
"هيا يا رفاق ، لدي هنا قضامة أظافر اصابع القدم.
You get past me,
لقد تجاوزتموني،
the guy behind me has a spoon."
الرجل ورائي لديه ملعقة ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
HK: He's a French robot.
هيذر نايت : انه روبوت فرنسي.
Data: A couple of New Jersey hunters are out in the woods.
داتا : صيادين من ولاية نيو جيرسي خرجوا إلى الغابة.
One of them falls to the ground.
وقع أحدهم على الأرض.
He does not seem to be breathing.
ويبدو أنه غير قادر على التنفس.
The other guy whips out his cell phone
الرجل الآخر التقط هاتفه النقال
and calls 911.
واتصل بـ 911.
He gasps to the operator, "My friend is dead.
وأخذ يصرخ لرجل الطوارئ، "صديقي مات.
What can I do?"
ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل؟ "
The operator says, "Just take it easy.
رجل الطوارئ يقول : "هدئ من روعك.
I can help.
أستطيع أن أساعدك.
First, let's make sure he's dead."
أولا ، دعنا تأكد من انه مات ".
There is a silence,
هناك صمت ،
and the operator hears a shot.
ورجل الطوارئ يسمع صوت طلقة رصاصة.
The guy's voice comes back on the line,
صوت الرجل يأتي مرة أخرى على الخط ،
"Okay, now what?"
"حسنا ، وماذا نفعل الآن؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Question: Why is television called a medium?
السؤال : لماذا يسمى التلفزيون بـ "الوسط"؟
Anyone?
أي شخص يعرف الجواب؟
Because it's neither rare nor well done.
لأنه ليس بـ"نيئ" ولا "متقن" الاستواء.
But to be completely honest with you,
ولكن لأكون صادق معكم ،
I kind of love television.
إنني أحب التلفاز نوعاً ما.
Any of you like television? Audience: Yes.
هل منكم من يحب التلفاز؟ (الجمهور : نعم)
Data: I find it incredibly educational.
أجده تعليمي ومفيد بشكل كبير.
Actually, as soon as someone turns it on,
في الواقع ، حالما يقوم أحداً بتشغيله،
I go into the other room and read.
أذهب إلى الغرفة الأخرى وأقرأ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's all for now.
هذا كل ما لدي الآن.
Was that okay for my first time?
هل كان أدائي جيدًا كأول مرة؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You've been a great audience.
لقد كنتم جمهورًا رائعًا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
HK: Yay.
هيثر نايت : ياي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So this is actually the first time
في الحقيقة هذه فعلاً المرة الأولى
we've ever done live audience feedback to a performance.
التي قمنا بتجربة الأداء وردات الفعل من خلال جمهور.
So thank you all for being a part of it.
لذا شكرا لكم جميعا لكونكم جزءًا منه.
There's a lot more to come.
هناك المزيد في المستقبل.
And we hope to learn a lot about robot expression.
ونأمل أن نتعلم الكثير عن التعبير لدى الروبوتات.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)